Guide to the Allison Davis Papers 1932-1984
University of Chicago Library
- Series IV: Course Materials
  - Subseries 3: Ph.D. Abstracts and Proposals
    - Wilson, Peter A., 1965 (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - Winkley, Carol K., 1963 (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - Wolf, Richard, 1963 (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - Wood, Vivian, 1960 (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - Zeeman, Sarah, undated (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - Subseries 4: M.A. Theses
    - Bagur, J. Susana, "A Consideration of Some Aspects of Non-Directive Play-Therapy as Applied to Child-Rearing Procedures in the Home and at School," 1964 (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - Bakule, Joanne C., "The Comic Situation as a Measurement of Children's Adjustment," 1963 (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Bloom, Sophie, "Acculturation and School-Learning Among Three Lower-Status Groups," 1960 (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - Curtis, Celestine, "Intelligence-Test Scores of Kindergarten Children of Different Social Classes," 1949 (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Hodges, Delores J., "Case Study Analysis of Five Secondary Students with Severe Reading Disabilities," 1973 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - McCamy, Edward D., "Speech and Language Development in the Mentally Retarded," 1964 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Perlmutter, Freda S., "Moral Development of the Child," 1957 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Rollerson, Yvonne, "The Negro Adolescent's Self-Concept," 1961 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Surratt, Carolyn, "Cultural Factors in Children's Solutions of Verbal Problems," 1946 (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Weddington, Rachel T., "The Relative Influence of Social Class and Color on the Stereotypes of Young Children," undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
- Series V: Research Files
  Series V contains Allison Davis' research files. The files follow, chronologically, the research projects during his career. The series itself has been arranged into eight subseries: (1) Natchez Project; (2) American Council on Education; (3) Carnegie-Myrdal Study; (4) Child-rearing and Psychological Development; (5) Child-rearing in Lower Status Families; (6) Acculturation Project; (7) Intelligence Testing; and (8) Young Adulthood Project.
  This series includes original drafts, manuscripts, lectures, research notes, course materials, correspondence, and field notes. Authorship of papers, presentations, and lectures should be attributed to Davis unless otherwise noted. All course numbers and titles refer to University of Chicago course offerings and Davis is assumed to be the course instructor unless some other indication is offered.
  Correspondence, notes, and bibliographies are at the beginning of each subseries. These are followed by manuscripts and drafts of Davis' written work and lectures, as well as course and seminar materials. These in turn are succeeded by material pertinent to other authors, institutions, and related subject areas. Miscellaneous items like clippings and reprint sets are found at the end of each subseries.
  Subseries 1: Natchez Project, and the classic work Deep South, includes field data, notes, and correspondence, as well as working drafts and manuscripts. A bound copy of Davis' Ph.D. dissertation, "Caste and Economic Stratification in the Deep South," is also present. Since Davis collaborated closely with Burleigh and Mary Gardner on all phases of the Natchez project from field work beginning in 1933 to final publication in 1942, it is difficult to determine the relative contributions of each of the authors to the manuscript materials collected here.
  Subseries 2: American Council on Education is divided into two sub-subseries: American Youth Commission and the Division on Child Development and Teacher Personnel. Davis's association with the American Youth Commission (1938-1939) was undertaken while teaching at Dillard University in New Orleans, and eventually lead to the publication of Children of Bondage with John Dollard. Included are interview data pertinent to that study, as well as manuscript drafts of Children of Bondage. The material pertinent to the Division on Child Development and Teacher Personnel is composed mainly of work group and seminar papers submitted for discussion by its various members.
  Subseries 3: Carnegie-Myrdal Study contains materials on another of Davis's projects that studied African American life in the United States. Davis consulted on the project and undertook a specific research task, the investigation of churches, lodges, and other associations among African Americans in Natchez and New Orleans. At the same time, he directed the investigations of St. Clair Drake into similar institutions in Chicago. Present are both Davis's and Drake's research memoranda, as well as correspondence from Gunnar Myrdal, the project director.
  Subseries 4: Child-rearing and Psychological Development is mainly concerned with a proposed work on this topic, circa 1962. Book outlines, chapter drafts, research materials, and related interview data are included.
  Subseries 5: Child-rearing in Lower Status Families, was the early work of Davis and Havighurst, which eventually formed the basis of Father of the Man as well as numerous scholarly articles. A substantial amount of interview data was collected as part of these case studies. The Newbury Center Materials refer to data gathered as a result of contacts initiated through the Newbury Center, a nursery school with outreach programs in the African American community. The primary research occurred from 1942 to 1944. The Hyde Park Neighborhood House Materials refer to data collected among lower status white families loosely connected by their association with this community center. Primary field research extended from 1942 to 1946, but some as late as 1949.
  Subseries 6: Acculturation Project, initiated in the early 1940s, proposed to investigate the role of the public schools in the assimilation and acculturation of children from diverse cultural and ethnic backgrounds. Three different sites with varying approaches to the issue were selected, California, Hawaii, and Brazil. Manuscripts dealing with the Californian and Hawaiian situations, as well as interview data from California, are included. The Brazil study was delayed and finally dropped though some pertinent notes and correspondence are represented.
  Subseries 7: Intelligence Testing materials are organized into three sub-subseries: General, School Studies, and Davis Tests. General contains correspondence, including that from the World Book Company and Kenneth Eells, as well as notes, manuscripts, and reprints. The School Studies include data from specific research conducted in Rockford and Gary schools, and materials from the General Education Board which sponsored much of that research. Davis Tests concerns the development of the test instruments themselves. It should be noted that there were several tests developed in the course of this research which at various times were called by various names--Davis Tests, Davis-Hess Tests, Davis-Eells Tests. This developmental process seems to have been relatively fluid with subsequent tests developing out of previous ones.
  Subseries 8: Young Adulthood Project includes manuscripts and reprints which both informed and emerged from the project; research memoranda, containing a series of numbered memoranda written by members of the Project; and interview data, incorporating material from both the early and late phases of the Project spanning a period from 1952-1962. Where possible Davis's groupings of interview data have been followed as, for example, in the entries "Kewpies," and "Negro Cases." The remainder of the material has been arranged alphabetically by informant name.
  - Subseries 1: Natchez Project
    - Notes, undated (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Note cards, sanctions, schools, Brumfield School, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Field notebook, 1933-1934 (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - "Caste and Economic Stratification in the Deep South," Ph.D. dissertation, 1941 (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Deep South, "Caste, Class, and Negro Schools," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Deep South, "Class in the Colored Society," manuscripts, charts, notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 3-6)
    - Deep South, "Courts and Crime," manuscript, undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Deep South, "Analysis of Cliques," manuscripts, charts, notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Deep South, "Analysis of Cliques," "Clique Analysis II, III--Superordination and Subordination," manuscript, notes, chart, undated (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Deep South, "Analysis of Cliques," white cliques, manuscripts, charts, notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 10-11)
    - Deep South, "Analysis of Social Classes," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 29, Folder 1-3)
    - Deep South, "The Caste System," manuscripts, undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Deep South, "Government and Politics," manuscript, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Deep South, "Preface to the 1965 Edition," manuscripts, 1965 (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Gardner, Burleigh B., "Principles of Social Organization," outline, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Gardner, Burleigh B., "Race Relationships in a Mississippi Community," Ph.D. dissertation, 1936 (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Gardner, Burleigh B., Mary R. Gardner, and Martin B. Loeb, "Social Status and Education in a Southern Community," reprint, 1942 (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Warner, W. Lloyd, "The Present Conditions of Studies of the Individual in Relation to Society," manuscript, undated (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Subseries 2: American Council on Education
    - Sub-subseries 1: American Youth Commission
      - Sub-sub-subseries 1: General
        - Notes, correspondence, memoranda, outlines, partial manuscripts, 1938-1940 (Box 30, Folder 1-3)
        - American Youth Tests, test materials, correspondence, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 4)
        - Color and status within Negro group, notes, undated (Box 30, Folder 5)
        - Delinquency, correspondence, bibliographies, notes, 1936 (Box 30, Folder 6)
        - Review of A Black Civilization by W. Lloyd Warner, manuscript, notes, ca. 1937 (Box 30, Folder 7)
        - "Basic Processes in His Socialization," manuscripts, correspondence, notes, 1939 (Box 30, Folder 8)
        - "Deprivations of the Negro Caste," manuscript, notes, undated (Box 30, Folder 9)
        - "Education and the Negro Community," manuscript, undated (Box 30, Folder 10)
        - "The Negro Adolescent," manuscript, undated (Box 30, Folder 11)
        - "A Proposal to Establish a Unit for Child Study and for the Social and Emotional Orientation of the Negro Child," with John Dollard, manuscripts, transcript, notes, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 12)
        - "The Study of Society," Dillard University, lecture transcript, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 13)
        - "Why People Work," manuscript, undated (Box 30, Folder 14)
        - Dollard, John, "The Dozens," manuscript, correspondence, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 15)
        - Institute of Human Relations, Synopsis of Research Conference on Social Classes, manuscript, 1939 (Box 30, Folder 16)
        - National Youth Administration of Georgia, Statewide Public Forums Project, minutes, outlines, questionnaires, 1938 (Box 30, Folder 17)
        - Warner, W. Lloyd and Allison Davis, "A Comparative Study of American Caste," manuscripts, outlines, notes, 1939 (Box 31, Folder 1-2)
        - Reprints, pamphlets, 1938-1939 (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Sub-sub-subseries 2: Interview Data
        - [Learning processes of Southern Whites], unidentified interviewer, [Olive], journal, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
        - Methods and strategies, manuscripts, transcripts, notes, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 5)
        - Special schedule, occupational history, notes, undated (3) (Box 31, Folder 6-8)
        - Edna Dunn, Elizabeth Davis, interviewer, transcripts, medical records, notes, 1938-1939 (Box 31, Folder 9-10)
        - Alice Hawkins, John Nealy, interviewer, transcript, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 11)
        - Nancy Hudson, Chicago case study summary, 1937 (Box 31, Folder 12)
        - Mrs. Johnson, Gladys Carroll, interviewer, transcript, notes, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 13)
        - Lorraine Mathieu, Claude Haydel, interviewer, transcripts, notes, 1938 (2) (Box 31, Folder 14-15)
        - Ralph Rochon, Gladys Green, interviewer, transcripts, notes, 1938 (Box 31, Folder 16)
        - Ralph Rochon, G. Sartor, "Psychological Study of Ralph Rochon," manuscript, undated (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - Sub-sub-subseries 3: Children of Bondage
        - Caste analysis by classes, charts, notes, undated (Box 32, Folder 1)
        - Revisions, comments, correspondence, 1939 (Box 32, Folder 2)
        - "Author's Note," Allison Davis, "Author's Note," John Dollard, manuscripts, title pages, contents pages, notes, undated (Box 32, Folder 3)
        - "The Subject and Its Setting," manuscripts, undated (Box 32, Folder 4)
        - "The Mystery of Personality," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 5)
        - "The Lower Classes," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 6)
        - "Frightened Amazon," manuscripts, undated (Box 32, Folder 7)
        - "Laughing Girl," manuscripts, undated (Box 32, Folder 8)
        - "Nameless Boy," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 9)
        - "Creole Miss," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 10)
        - "Ellen Hill, the Winner," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 11)
        - "The Black Sheep," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 12)
        - "A Case for the Reader," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 13)
        - "How It Feels to Be Lower Caste," manuscripts, undated (Box 32, Folder 14)
        - "What Is Social Class?" manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 15)
        - Davis, Elizabeth B., Review of Children of Bondage by Allison Davis and John Dollard, manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Division on Child Development and Teacher Personnel
      - General, Lawrence K. Frank, reprint, 1939 (Box 32, Folder 17)
      - General, Margaret Mead, "Prefatory Note to Bibliography," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 18)
      - General, George Sheviakov, "Study of Students' Reactions to Adults," manuscript, 1942 (Box 32, Folder 19)
      - General, W. Lloyd Warner, "The Present Condition of Studies of the Individual in Relation to Society," manuscript, undated (Box 32, Folder 20)
      - Notes, partial manuscripts, 1938-1941 (Box 32, Folder 21)
      - Bibliographies, 1940-1942 (Box 32, Folder 22)
      - Bibliographies, children in war time, undated (Box 32, Folder 23)
      - Boy Scouts, questionnaires, undated (Box 32, Folder 24)
      - Case study materials, manuscripts, notes, 1941 (Box 32, Folder 25)
      - Staff in personnel, manuscripts, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - "Conceptual Framework for a Study of the Nature and Development of the Child," manuscripts, bibliographies, charts, notes, 1941-1942 (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - Barker, Roger G., "Preliminary Outline of Important Viewpoints in Child Development," "Science and Education," manuscripts, outlines, notes, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 3)
      - Bell, Reginald, "Outline of Major Emphases Arising from Child Development Research Which Are of Usefulness to Education," manuscript, summary, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 4)
      - Brown, J. F., "The Topological Approach to Experimental Psychopathology," manuscript, 1942 (Box 33, Folder 5)
      - Freeman, Frank S., "Growth and Development of the Organism," "Tentative Statement of Concepts of Development," manuscripts, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 6)
      - Gage, Catherine J., "Human Growth and Development and Their Implications for Education," "Psychophysical Organism," manuscripts, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 7)
      - Lewin, Kurt, "Survey of Activities at Iowa [Child Welfare Research Station] in Recent Years," lecture transcript, 1941 (Box 33, Folder 8)
      - Murphy, Lois B., "Backgrounds of Sarah Lawrence Exploratory Courses--Psychology," manuscript, 1941 (Box 33, Folder 9)
      - Olson, Willard C., "Concepts of Human Development," manuscripts, outlines, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 10)
      - Prescott, Daniel A., "Inter-University Collaboration to Further Research in Human Development and Behavior and to Extend the Use of Research in the Education of Professional Persons," "Organizing Framework of Scientific Concepts About Human Development and Behavior," "Patterns of Physical Growth in Adolescence," manuscripts, 1940-1944 (Box 33, Folder 11)
      - Ralston, Arlene, "Human Behavioral Development," "Overview of Human Growth and Development," manuscripts, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 12)
      - Redl, Fritz, "The Concept of Adjustment," "The Concept of Maturity," "The Usage of the Terms Normal and Abnormal," manuscripts, summaries, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 13)
      - Sanford, R. Nevitt, "Constellations of Factors in the Family," manuscript, 1941 (Box 33, Folder 14)
      - Somers, G. T., "An Overview of the Concepts Involved in the Growth and Development of the Organism," "Tentative View of Child Development," manuscripts, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 15)
      - Stoke, Stuart M., "Biological Knowledge for Teachers," "Keeping Behavior Journals," "The Social Analysis of the Classroom," "Synthesis of Concepts on Child Development," manuscripts, summaries, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 16)
      - Tryon, Caroline, "Concepts in an Overview of Human Development," "Study of Adolescents," manuscripts, 1940-1941 (Box 33, Folder 17)
      - Washburne, John N., "Biological Concepts Which Are Important for Teachers," "Outline of Major Concepts Concerning Growth and Development," manuscripts, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - Subseries 3: Carnegie-Myrdal Study
    - Myrdal, Gunnar, correspondence, manuscripts, 1939 (Box 33, Folder 19)
    - "The Negro Church and Associations in the Lower South," manuscript, 1940 (Box 33, Folder 20)
    - Drake, J. G. St. Clair, "Materials Available for a Study of Churches and Associations Among Negroes in Chicago," manuscript, ca. 1940 (Box 33, Folder 21)
    - Drake, J. G. St. Clair, "The Negro Church and Associations in Chicago," manuscript, 1940 (2) (Box 33, Folder 22-23)
    - Frazier, Edward F., "Introductory Statement of the Relation of Culture and Personality," manuscripts, undated (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified, "A Bibliography of Racial and Cultural Contact," undated (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 4: Child-rearing and Psychological Development
    - Holt, Rinehart, and Winston, correspondence, contract, 1960 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Notes, summaries, undated (Box 34, Folder 4-5)
    - Bibliographies, notes, 1961 (Box 34, Folder 6-7)
    - Education 304, 336, lecture notes, bibliography, undated (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Interview data, Education 311, manuscript, transcripts, notes, 1956 (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - Interview data, Education 346, manuscripts, notes, drawings, 1961 (Box 34, Folder 10-11)
    - Interview data, age and sex typing, manuscript, undated (Box 34, Folder 12)
    - Interview data, I. Q. comparisons, 5th Grade, charts, notes, undated (Box 34, Folder 13)
    - Interview data, representative samples of reading materials and tests, notes, 1957 (Box 34, Folder 14)
    - Interview data, toilet training, Mary S. Carson, interviewer, manuscripts, notes, 1961 (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Interview data, toilet training, Mary S. Carson, "A Study of the Toilet Training Process," "Toilet Training--Five Case Studies," manuscripts, correspondence, bibliographic materials, 1960-1965 (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Outline of book on child psychology, partial manuscripts, notes, 1962 (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Outline of book on child psychology, oral development, manuscript, notes, undated (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Outline of book on child psychology, psychological development in the family, notes, 1942, 1960 (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - Outline of book on child psychology, role, manuscript, notes, clipping, ca. 1960 (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Outline of book on child psychology, socialization of young children, manuscripts, tables, notes, undated (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - "A (Beginning of Chapter)," manuscripts, undated (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - "Child Rearing in Two Preliterate Societies," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - "The Child in the Social System of the Family," manuscripts, correspondence, notes, 1960 (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - "Perspective on Child Development," partial manuscript, notes, undated (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - "The Range of Environments," manuscript, undated (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - "The Social Roles of Child and Parent," manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - "Socialization of Child in In-Migrant Chicago Families," with Benjamin Wright, grant proposal, manuscripts, financial statements, notes, 1961-1963 (Box 36, Folder 6-7)
    - Foreman, Jack D., "Academic Achievement, Personality Variables, Social Acceptance, Extra Curricular Activities, and After School Success," manuscript, memorandum, 1960 (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Hess, Robert D., W. Patrick Dickson, Gary D. Price, Deborah J. Leong, "The Different Functions of Parenting and Child Care," manuscript, undated (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Intercultural Education News, newsletters, 1942 (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Jamison, Donald, "Aggression in Adolescents," manuscript, undated (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Kim, Chung Han, "Child Rearing in Korea," student paper, 1956 (Box 36, Folder 12)
    - Saxonberg, Sonja S., "Children's Images of Their Fathers," manuscript, undated (Box 36, Folder 13)
    - Stone, Shelley C., "A Study of the Relationship Among Values, Family Characteristics and Personality Variables of Adolescents," dissertation abstract, memorandum, 1960 (Box 36, Folder 14)
    - Young, Michael and Peter Willmott, "Family and Kinship in East London," manuscripts, undated (Box 36, Folder 15)
    - Reprints, 1949-1961 (Box 36, Folder 16)
  - Subseries 5: Child-rearing in Lower Status Families
    - Sub-subseries 1: General
      - Cultural development of children in minority groups, note cards, undated (Box 36, Folder 17)
      - "A Comparison of the Chicago and Harvard Studies of Social Class Differences in Child Rearing," "Social Class and Color Differences in Child Rearing," both with Robert J. Havighurst, reprints, manuscripts, notes, 1946, 1955 (Box 36, Folder 18)
      - "Early Training in American Cultural Forms," charts, undated (Box 36, Folder 19)
      - "Explanations of Contradictory Findings in Child Rearing and Social Class Studies," notes, ca. 1960 (Box 36, Folder 20)
      - Father of the Man, with Robert J. Havighurst, manuscripts, notes, undated (Box 36, Folder 21-22)
      - Father of the Man, "Brothers and Sisters," manuscripts, notes, 1945 (Box 37, Folder 1-3)
      - Father of the Man, Robert J. Havighurst, "The Korbus Family," outline, notebook, ca. 1943-1945 (Box 37, Folder 4)
      - "Social Class and Color Differences in Child-Rearing," with Robert J. Havighurst, manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 5)
      - "They're All Jealous," manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 6)
      - Bronfenbrenner, Urie, "Socialization and Social Class Through Time and Space," manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 7)
      - Cozine, June, "An Evaluation of the Foods and Nutrition Work as Offered by the State Supported Colleges and Universities of Missouri," manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 8)
      - Unidentified, "Experimental Methods in the Field of Food Habits," manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 9)
      - Unidentified, "The Interviewing Method," manuscript, undated (Box 37, Folder 10)
      - Unidentified, "Research on the Development of Indian Personality," manuscript, 1942 (Box 37, Folder 11)
      - Unidentified, "Summary of Research on Indians in St. Louis and Chicago," undated (Box 37, Folder 12)
      - Reprints, 1957 (Box 37, Folder 13)
    - Sub-subseries 2: Newbury Center Material